<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Serge Rey</title><link href="http://sergerey.org/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://sergerey.org/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://sergerey.org/</id><updated>2015-10-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>GWU Symposium</title><link href="http://sergerey.org/gwu-symposium.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-10-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Serge Rey</name></author><id>tag:sergerey.org,2015-10-05:gwu-symposium.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am looking forward to participating in the &lt;a href="https://cps.gwu.edu/gws-sustainable-urban-planning-research-symposium"&gt;Sustainable Urban Planning Research Symposium&lt;/a&gt; at George Washington University which is examining applications of regional modeling and spatial analysis in urban planning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will be presenting our work on developing new spatial and saptiotemporal methods as part of &lt;a href="Http://PySAL.org"&gt;PySAL&lt;/a&gt;, and discussing how these have been used in applied research on economic development, housing markets and segregation.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="big data"></category><category term="urban planning"></category><category term="pysal"></category></entry><entry><title>Markdown Services</title><link href="http://sergerey.org/markdown-services.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Serge Rey</name></author><id>tag:sergerey.org,2015-06-30:markdown-services.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Services_menu"&gt;Services&lt;/a&gt; are one of the most under appreciated, and therefore underutilized, aspects of OS X. Every so often I am reminded how helpful these things can be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem of course, is that the reminders seem like &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_swan_theory"&gt;Black Swan effects&lt;/a&gt;, so remembering that I have set them up in the first place becomes a problem. I think that is something that  fixed only when one inculcates their use in a regular fashion. Sort of like muscle memory for the brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As most of my writing starts in &lt;a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax"&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt;, I find that the &lt;a href="http://brettterpstra.com/projects/markdown-service-tools/"&gt;Markdown Services&lt;/a&gt; by one &lt;a href="http://brettterpstra.com"&gt;Brett Terpstra&lt;/a&gt; can be a major productivity booster.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="markdown"></category></entry><entry><title>Spatial Econometrics Documentation for PySAL</title><link href="http://sergerey.org/spatial-econometrics-documentation-for-pysal.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-12-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Serge Rey</name></author><id>tag:sergerey.org,2014-12-31:spatial-econometrics-documentation-for-pysal.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just in time for the New Year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="cover" src="images/mse.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Available from &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0986342106/sr=8-1/qid=1420070700/ref=olp_product_details?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;me=&amp;amp;qid=1420070700&amp;amp;sr=8-1"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book is the definitive user’s guide to the spatial regression
functionality in the software packages GeoDa and GeoDaSpace, as well as the
spreg module in the PySAL library –-all developed at the GeoDa Center for
Geospatial Analysis and Computation. The book provides the techniques to test
for and estimate spatial effects in linear regression models, addressing both
spatial dependence (spatial autoregressive models) as well as spatial
heterogeneity (spatial regimes models). The book also serves as an
introduction and a practical guide to spatial econometrics in that it covers
the methodological principles and formal results that underlie the various
estimation methods, test procedures and model characteristics computed by the
software. While the classical maximum likelihood estimation is included, the
book’s coverage emphasizes modern techniques based on the principle of
generalized method of moments (GMM).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="pysal"></category></entry><entry><title>CyberGIS 2014</title><link href="http://sergerey.org/cybergis-2014.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-08-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Serge Rey</name></author><id>tag:sergerey.org,2014-08-27:cybergis-2014.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Panel" src="images/cybergis14.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week I attended the &lt;a href="http://cybergis.illinois.edu/events/cybergis14/"&gt;Second International Conference on CyberGIS and Geodesign&lt;/a&gt;. We presented a few talks on our work related to the CyberGIS project, and one of the highlights for me was a very engaging panel with old friends &lt;a href="http://web.env.auckland.ac.nz/people_profiles/gahegan_m/"&gt;Mark Gahegan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://parker.ou.edu/~myuan/"&gt;May Yuan&lt;/a&gt;,  &lt;a href="http://dusk.geo.orst.edu/"&gt;Dawn Wright&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.cigi.illinois.edu/shaowen/"&gt;Shaowen Wang&lt;/a&gt; as emcee.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="cybergis"></category></entry><entry><title>Heat Map Gone Wild</title><link href="http://sergerey.org/heat-map-gone-wild.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-08-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Serge Rey</name></author><id>tag:sergerey.org,2014-08-10:heat-map-gone-wild.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I stumbled on this rather striking example of cartography gone wild:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="heat map" src="images/ws_heatmap.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Source: &lt;a href="http://www.wallstreetotc.com/heatmap-broadview-network-shows-us-states-best-internet-speed/26807/"&gt;Wall Street OTC&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So many things a cartographer could say about this. For starters, heat maps are typically used with raster data and
the state map depicted here uses a vector representation. Beyond that, the
color scheme induces a good bout of cognitive dissonance in the reader. A
&lt;em&gt;heat&lt;/em&gt; map implies that hotter colors are associated with higher attribute
values (see an example &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heat_map#mediaviewer/File:WOA09_sea-surf_SAL_AYool.png"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). But think of the viewer, what color would
be interpreted as hotter, red or green? Yeah, the red states of course. Actually, 
no, the green states (green as in go fast, I guess?) have higher broadband
speeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ouch.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="visualization"></category></entry><entry><title>NSF Award for New Approaches for Spatial Distribution Dynamics</title><link href="http://sergerey.org/nsf-award-for-new-approaches-for-spatial-distribution-dynamics.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-08-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Serge Rey</name></author><id>tag:sergerey.org,2014-08-03:nsf-award-for-new-approaches-for-spatial-distribution-dynamics.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am very excited that my recent proposal on new approaches for spatial distribution dynamics will be funded. From the &lt;a href="http://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1421935"&gt;Award Abstract&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research project will improve understanding of spatial inequality dynamics through methodological advances in measurement and modeling. Understanding the nature of spatial inequality dynamics is vital to both basic social science and to public policy, yet existing methods and models provide incomplete views of these spatial dynamics. While a central focus of inequality research has been on the evolution of the aggregate income distribution, much less attention has been directed at the spatial pattern of inequality and pattern dynamics. Spatial inequalities can have important implications for social cohesion, economic growth, and the design of policies targeted at reducing the level of inequality. The advances produced in the project will have wide applicability. In addition to spatial income inequality dynamics, many other social and economic phenomena have distributions that evolve in space and time. Software packages will be delivered as open-source projects and accompanied with extensive tutorials and documentation to facilitate broad dissemination across the social sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research project will develop new analytical methods for the study of spatial dynamics of income inequality; specifically, new approaches will be developed to measuring changes in the distributional characteristics of those dynamics that incorporate their spatial dependence and heterogeneity. The new approaches will include both global measures that report summary properties of the spatial dynamics as well as local indicators that can be used to identify hot-spots of locations that are important drivers of the overall dynamics or are outliers from the global trends. Analytical and simulation based evaluations of the statistical properties of the new measures will be conducted, and empirical applications involving regional income inequalities will be carried out. These new analytics will be incorporated into enhanced versions of two open-source spatial analysis packages: Python Spatial Analysis Library and Space-Time Analysis of Regional Systems. The former provides social scientists who wish to develop custom applications with access to a modular library that can be used in conjunction with existing software to enable the new space-time analytics. The latter is a user-friendly analytical and visualization package that can facilitate exploratory investigation of spatial distribution dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="research"></category><category term="NSF"></category><category term="PySAL"></category><category term="STARS"></category></entry><entry><title>Big Data Conundrum</title><link href="http://sergerey.org/big-data-conundrum.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Serge Rey</name></author><id>tag:sergerey.org,2014-07-27:big-data-conundrum.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Interesting piece by &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/07/27/upshot/hold-the-phone-a-big-data-conundrum.html?hpw&amp;amp;action=click&amp;amp;pgtype=Homepage&amp;amp;version=HpHedThumbWell&amp;amp;module=well-region&amp;amp;region=bottom-well&amp;amp;WT.nav=bottom-well&amp;amp;_r=0"&gt;Sendhil Mullainathan&lt;/a&gt; in the NY Times: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, if attention on new devices is what makes old ones feel slow, why are the spikes on Apple product release dates, and not when the company announces the new products? In 2008, for example, the iPhone3G was announced a full month before its release. There was a spike at the release, but not at the announcement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This data has an even more benign explanation. Every major iPhone release coincides with a major new operating system release. Though Apple would not comment on the matter, one could speculate — and many have — that a new operating system, optimized for new phones, would slow down older phones. This could also explain the Samsung-iPhone difference: Because only 18 percent of Android users have the latest operating systems on their phones, whereas 90 percent of iPhone users do, any slowdown from a new operating system would be naturally bigger for iPhones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure that these are the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; two possible reasons for the spike in searches for the iPhone around the release dates however. Wouldn't people who are contemplating a purchase of the new phone also be searching for information on all the new features? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The larger point of the article is spot-on though, "big data" can uncover patterns but the mechanisms behind those patterns need to be identified by other means.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="big data"></category><category term="apple"></category></entry><entry><title>PySAL 1.8 Released</title><link href="http://sergerey.org/pysal-18-released.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Serge Rey</name></author><id>tag:sergerey.org,2014-07-25:pysal-18-released.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We normally ship &lt;a href="http://pysal.readthedocs.org/en/v1.8/"&gt;PySAL&lt;/a&gt; on a six-month release cycle, once at the end of January and again the end of July. This year due to travel schedules (it is summer after all) we shipped 1.8 one week early. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of work on the testing infrastructure, bug fixes and optimizations. One new &lt;a href="http://pysal.readthedocs.org/en/v1.8/library/contrib/index.html"&gt;contrib  module&lt;/a&gt; that provides for interaction between  PySAL and &lt;a href="http://www.rise-group.org/risem/clusterpy/"&gt;clusterpy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pysal"></category></entry><entry><title>Editor of Geographical Analysis</title><link href="http://sergerey.org/editor-of-geographical-analysis.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Serge Rey</name></author><id>tag:sergerey.org,2014-07-01:editor-of-geographical-analysis.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The month begins with a new position as editor of &lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/10.1111/(ISSN)1538-4632"&gt;Geographical Analysis&lt;/a&gt;. I am honored to serve as the 10th editor of GA and am looking forward to working with an outstanding &lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/journal/10.1111/(ISSN)1538-4632/homepage/EditorialBoard.html"&gt;editorial board&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="geographical analysis"></category></entry></feed>